Guide to the Fort Missoula (Mont.) Collection 1877-1899
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Fort Missoula (Mont.) Collection
1877-1899
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 100
Fort Missoula (Mont.)
0.5 linear feet
This collection includes photocopies and originals of materials related to the construction and daily business of early Fort Missoula, and also contains information on the 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps.
In part, copied from originals located in the United States National Archives.
Between 1867 and 1876 citizens in Missoula, Montana Territory, pleaded, protested, and petitioned for a military post. While Indian problems usually initiated each round of concern, local newspapers editorials touted the value of a military presence for encouraging immigration and business. In 1876, the War Department approved a company post and appropriated funds. Construction began in the summer of 1877 but Indian trouble delayed the work. Barracks and non-commissioned officer's quarters were completed in February 1878, and in mid-summer of the same year officer's quarters were finished.
On May 12, 1896, Fort Missoula's 2nd Lieutenant James A. Moss received permission to organize the 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps, the first of its kind in the country. The Corps, consisting of eight black enlisted men, practiced riding in formation, drilling, scaling fences up to nine-feet high, fording streams, and pedaling 40 miles a day. After a successful trek to Yellowstone National Park, the Corps took on the challenge of riding from Missoula to St. Louis, Missouri. That forty-one day journey in the summer of 1897 was the last for the Bicycle Corps. By 1898 war with Spain was probable and military priorities shifted.
Fort Missoula remained active for a number of years as a military installation. It also housed the Civilian Conservation Corps during the 1930s and Italian, German, and Japanese internees during WWII. There were no regular military forces at Fort Missoula after 1947.
Fort Missoula was formally decommissioned in April, 2001.
This collection includes photocopies and originals of materials related to the construction and daily business of early Fort Missoula. The collection also includes photocopies of several reports on the travels of the 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps in 1896 and 1897.
This collection is divided into two series:
Series I: Construction and daily business of Fort Missoula, 0.2 linear feet, 1877-1889
Series II: Reports on 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps trips, 0.3 linear feet, 1896-1897
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The portion of this collection that deals with the Fort construction was donated by Miss Zella Smith in April 1961 with the addition of the photocopied letter donated by Kermit Edmonds on an unknown date. The 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps reports were copied from the U. S. National Archives on an unknown date. The microfilm copy of the 1883-84 letterbook was donated by an unknown donor on an unknown date
Montana State University holds a collection of Fort Missoula building plans in its Historic American Buildings Survey Collection.
The Historical Museum at Fort Missoula holds a considerable collection of materials related to the history of the Fort.
Fortification--Montana
Fort Missoula (Mont.); Montan--History, Militar--19th century
United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 25th. Bicycle Corps
Montana; Diaries; African Americans; Military; Transportation
- Construction and daily business of Fort Missoula, 1877-1889; Series I; 0.2 linear feet
  This series includes a photocopies of Fort Missoula letterbooks from 1877 with correspondence about the military's activities from constructing the Fort to defending Montana Territory civilians and a microfilm copy of a Fort Missoula letterbook from Jan. 2, 1883 to May 9, 1884. Other materials relate to construction and supplies.
  - Photocopy of letterbook, 1877 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Photocopy of letterbook, 1883-1884 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Photocopy of letter to A.M. Holter & Co., 1877 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Design for root house, 1878 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Estimate of Quartermaster's Shares, 1886 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Letter to Lt. C.A. Devol, 1889 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Bound letterbook photocopy, 1879-1881 (Volume 1)
  - Fort Missoula letterbook, 1883-1884 (Microfilm 1)
- Reports on 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps trips, 1896-1897; Series II; 0.3 linear feet
  This series includes detailed reports on the Bicycle Corps trips that include such information as weather, road or trail conditions, specific daily routes, equipment conditions, and the condition of the men in the Corps.
  - Report on 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps trip to Yellowstone, August ca. 1896 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Report on 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps trip, 1896 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Special Order for 25th Infantry, 1897 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Report on 25th Infantry Bicycle Corps trip, 1897 (Box-folder 1/10)